THE HUNCHBACK OF NOTRE DAME
Some years ago, while visiting...
or rather exploring Notre Dame,
the author of this book
found on one of the towers
this Greek word carved on the wall.
FATALITY
The word made the author wonder
what kind of tortured soul
would want to leave behind
this kind of infamy and crime
on the old cathedral.
Today, no trace remains
of this mysterious word,
nor of the tragic life it recalled.
Yet this book is based
on that one word.
Victor Hugo, February 1831.
- I am Jupiter.
- Me too!
I know it's rather bold
and too severe for a Feast,
but it offers a new moral
with many details
that are quite risqué.
How do you know that?
I am Pierre Gringoire, the author.
- Charity, please.
- Silence!
- Charity!
- Charity...
Faith and Hope!
Hope that the play will be good.
- Quiet, the Cardinal's here.
- And the Ambassadors.
To Hell with them!
Today is freedom for all!
- I am Jupiter!
- You've already told us!
Just listen!
They've all gone mad!
Michel, let me quieten them.
The Mystery is entitled,
"The Virgin Mary's judgement".
Charity!
Silence!
You'll see Venus, the Virgin Mary,
the Golden Dolphin
and the Queen of Golconda.
But when will it start?
Enough! Bring on the mummers!
We also have the Feast of Fools.
In Flanders,
they're up to all kinds of mischief.
It's a proper sight!
- Good day, Clopin!
- Greetings!
This beggar is a real king.
We met in Antwerp.
- I'm much travelled.
- Yes...
but in Antwerp you had no arms!
I was cured on a pilgrimage.
When suddenly...
the radiant Princess was chosen
by the Virgin Mary.
The Golden Dolphin,
heir to the French throne,
saw it in a dream...
Come, Angels, if you fear not!
That's not in the play!
At last, some foolery.
It was beginning to bore me.
- A Mystery with no music...
...is too mysterious, I'd say.
- I didn't say that.
- Don't worry. Leave it to me.
Good people!
I don't know what we're doing here
when we have a king to elect.
A play, however edifying,
should not shroud this other event.
Long live the fools!
Wait for me, Clopin.
The word of the people
is the Word of God.
But luckily, only once a year.
Clear that away!
- It's the grey man!
- Killjoy!
Sour face!
- It's allowed today.
- Not in the square.
- Everything's allowed!
- If you don't like it...
...we'll strip you!
- To your birthday suit!
Go to Hell!
Leave me.
Claude, the play can wait!
Lend your brother some money.
- For the Feast.
- This charade?!
- Where would my money go?
- To a cabaret.
- You have no soul.
- And yours is dead!
Mine's alive and in need of money!
- To the Devil with you!
- He's my friend!
Your meanness won't help me.
I'll turn to crime instead.
Master, I'm so grateful you came.
To see what? A disaster!
It's all gone.
Public, Cardinal, Ambassadors, music.
Those who go do not compare
to those who stay
and enjoy sacred music.
Djali!
The Feast of Fools has made her mad.
Esmeralda!
- It's Esmeralda!
- Gilles, don't you dare go!
Esmeralda?!
- Where is she from?
- Egypt.
She dares to dance on the square.
I'm trying to put a stop to it.
- A fearful creature.
- Indeed. She has ruined me.
No, the play was already ruined.
She has just finished the job.
In a light-footed way!
- Madame!
- It's the coronation.
Thank you.
- Here, take it.
- It's ours?
Today's a Feast. It's for you.
- And you?
- Everyday is a Feast.
Here.
Come, Djali.
Djali... The sound of far-off lands
which evoke dreams.
You hear, Djali? Say thanks.
He's not ugly or funny!
There's lots like him about!
He's the best. He's the winner.
Long live the King of Fools!
Clopin, King of Coins,
does the Court of Miracles approve?
You know him.
Is he any different?
I'll ask the Duke of Egypt,
King of gypsies.
He is already Emperor of Galilee.
Why refuse him other honours?
Not so fast! Here's the best!
Quasimodo!
Long live King Quasimodo!
Quasimodo, of course!
He grimaces from head to toe!
Move away!
Quasimodo, King of Fools!
The bells have made you deaf.
Deaf as a coot! Deaf as a boot!
King of the Deaf, hear our prayers.
He's so handsome!
She'll pay for that!
Once you've seen her,
you'll never love another.
What good is a bed without her?
- Ask her!
- No! Not because I'm shy, mind you.
I just know she's not for me.
Nor us, yet we are her Kings!
- So whose is she?
- Tell us... We'll kill him!
I can hear music.
Yes!
It's like the bells.
Like thunder and lightning!
I can hear it.
What are you doing all alone?
- Come on, tonight's for love.
- Tonight's for living.
- Sacrilege!
- He's a killjoy!
Judas!
Sleep, good folk! It's 11 o'clock!
It's 11 o'clock! Sleep, good folk!
Sleep?! Easier said than done.
If sleep had a house,
I'd knock at his door.
- Master...
- Go!
You've changed.
- You seem to have... grief.
- Grief?
What else can I have?
Life is no Feast for me.
Go fetch her!
Master...
- She's so beautiful.
- Too bad for her, too bad for me.
Is it my fault how she dances?
Is it my fault
her beauty drives me wild?
Go!
See?
You're trapped.
Help!
- The bell-ringer!
- The scoundrel!
Tie his legs up!
Arrest him!
- Only got one eye!
- Enough to look at girls!
- Thank you.
- Pretty mouth.
I'd love to see it in the light.
Beautiful!
Like a King's mistress!
You're trembling, my sweet.
I was so afraid.
You're not afraid of me
kidnapping you?
You're different. You rescued me.
What's your name?
- Phoebus.
- It's nice.
- It means "the Sun".
- The Sun...
- Where to?
- Where indeed?
A nightlong ride with the Sun,
till your horse stops at daybreak.
You are too lovely to wait till day!
There's a room.
The clean one upstairs.
Goodnight, Sun.
Am I to sleep alone?
- Sleep with your dreams!
- But you are my dream!
My dream for tonight.
Goodbye Sun. And thank you.
Pity! She was beautiful.
Beautiful, but a bit dishevelled.
That's just the way I like them!
Charity, please!
Last week I gave away
the shirt from my own back.
I myself have no money to eat.
Nor to afford a bed.
We're not asking about you...
We're asking for charity!
Give us a little, or else
we'll have the whole lot away!
You shouldn't have come here!
I don't disagree.
I am a victim of fate...
And somebody stole my hat.
- His hat!
- They took his hat!
- Who did?
- Here's one, for the meantime.
Look, a sinner!
He looks ripe for a hanging!
- Where am I?
- The Court of Miracles.
Then I'm not surprised...
A cripple just stole my hat.
Stole?!
He's moaning to us about stealing!
Are you so virtuous, then?
No, but I've never harmed anyone.
But you have broken the rules
of our kingdom!
You came in with no credentials.
- And he came in running!
- In such a hurry to die?
You're not really going to...
We like to see an honest man
swinging on a rope.
It's more honourable.
- What is your trade?
- I'm a poet.
In other words,
you are a liar and a beggar!
The noose makes the tongues
of poets and kings
look the same as a robber's.
But...
before you're hanged
you'll get a fair trial.
A man's about to meet his fate.
Poor devil!
But justice must be done!
And ours is as good as the King's.
He doles out justice in iron cages!
Cages much too small for me!
Come, my lovelies,
some justice will do us good!
Executioner, do your job!
- But I'm innocent!
- Like a lamb.
Innocent lambs makes better roasts!
I remember you.
You're the writer of that Mystery.
I am indeed the author of
"The Virgin Mary's Judgement".
I am Pierre Gringoire.
Is boring us to death
good reason not to die?
You seem repulsed.
You bourgeois are too idealistic!
- Now if you were a criminal...
- I'd like to become one!
Have you ever cut someone up?
No, but if I'd known I should have,
I'd have tried.
He seems willing!
He'll make a fine corpse!
Executioner, do your duty!
Wait! We used to say...
you can't hang a man
if some woman wants him.
That's taking bread from my mouth!
Don't worry!
You'll have plenty of time to eat.
You are lucky, little man.
Fortune smiles upon you.
You can choose
between a wench or the rope.
Either way I'm done for.
But I do prefer...
The wench!
Here, my lovely ladies!
Anyone fancy this one?
Hey, Colette! Elisabeth!
Marie and Marie!
Hey, Claude! Isabeau!
He'll cost you nothing!
Any takers?
One squeeze and I'd kill him!
Good for a kiss and cuddle.
But I'm past it!
I need someone useful.
- If I have him you'll be jealous!
- Cut him up, we'll share him!
You never find
exactly what you're looking for!
Friend, you've no luck!
Nobody want him?
Going... Going...
Gone! Hang him!
Wait!
- Are you hanging him?
- Unless you want him.
I'll take him.
- You're joking?!
- No.
Death may be fun for you,
but not for me.
She likes him!
I'd have let you hang and applauded.
Prepare the ceremony!
Throw it down.
Brother, she's your wife.
Sister, he's your husband.
For four years!
No curtains on the riverbank
No locks in the forest
The pretty girl runs
The pretty girl swims
Dressed only in secrets
Only the Sun can undress her.
Did you make that up?
Nothing is made up.
It's all planned.
I recall things.
My troubles or grief...
And my desires.
It seems simple for you.
What do you do, poet?
If it doesn't come, I look.
- Where? In there?
- Alas!
Poor Gringoire! Why be a poet?
I was a good-for-nothing...
I was orphaned at six.
I grew up and tried anything.
I was a soldier,
but I wasn't brave enough.
I was a monk,
but I wasn't devout enough.
And I'm not a good drinker.
So I became a poet.
I've written a few books!
600 pages on the comet of 1465.
600 pages on a shooting star?!
Boring!
But now it's over.
You can turn to crime!
- Crime?
- Yes.
At night people are in the street...
You wait for them...
And kill them!
Or you can just rob them!
- But I'm so clumsy.
- So be a beggar!
Blind... one-armed... crippled!
- It's up to you.
- But I'm in good health.
I just said it to scare you.
You can work with me and Djali.
Help her with her writing!
- She writes?!
- Like you and I.
She'll learn a new word.
Do you hear, Djali?
Phoebus!
That means "the Sun".
- I know.
- He was an archer god.
- God...
- There were many to choose from.
- I've chosen...
- The Court of Miracles!
I was tired, hungry and about to die.
Now I'm saved, fed and off to bed!
A bed and a woman!
What a woman! And she's mine!
It seems a bit hard.
And a little small for two.
Don't you agree?
I'm sleeping in there as always.
- Why did you marry me?
- I couldn't let you hang.
So you just wanted to save me
from the gallows?
Why else?
Why else?! I don't know...
Or rather I do, alas!
Goodnight, Gringoire. Sweet dreams.
- Charity!
- Wonderful thing, charity!
He's the King of Misers.
Thanks Your Majesty.
I'm getting too old
for all this climbing.
Let's hope it's worth it.
You'll see, Sire. He's a strange one.
Remember, Charmolue,
in front of Frollo I'm not the King.
I'm a friend from Touraine.
What are they doing up there?
- Thunder damage!
- May Notre Dame protect them.
Like me,
she'll have coins on her hat.
It's here, Sire.
He lives like a hermit.
Certain women's names
are so soft, so mysterious
one has only to pronounce them
during the experiment...
See, Sire, he's doing research.
He could hang for it.
What if he finds the secret of gold?
It would improve our finances.
And there's plenty
of other witches to burn!
Let's go in.
I have tried medicine
and astrology: nothing!
The human body: darkness!
The stars: darkness!
Master, I am a humble squire
from Touraine,
who bows before scientists,
but allow me to ask you a question.
What do you believe in?
- In God.
- Our Father.
What else?
I believe in alchemy.
Gold is the light.
Gold?
- Have you made gold?
- If I had...
I would be King of France,
instead of Louis.
- If the King heard...
- He'd merely ask after your work.
I have not worked for so long
without seeing before me
a light...
a flame!
A flame?!
Tell me, Master...
does your science
not displease Our Lady?
I am sure Our Lady keeps watch
over my work.
I respect men of science
and letters.
You, in particular.
Come soon to the Bastille,
where we may speak in peace.
Arise!
There is no King here.
We are too near Heaven.
Will you cast spells on us
with your bells?
Antichrist!
Son of a witch!
Half-formed freak!
Something's happening
in my good city!
Who are we whipping?
You should know,
as Procurer to the King.
It's Quasimodo, Sire.
The people's pet hate.
The bell-ringer.
I can feel each lash myself.
Master Frollo brought him up.
He tried to teach him to read.
What has he done, this naughty boy?
He assaulted a gypsy girl last night.
Master, don't take it to heart.
After all, he's not a monk!
A man who lives apart from others,
away from life,
far from women,
even despised by women...
Nature lays horrible traps
for men like that.
This trap was particularly lovely!
Making temptation more dreadful!
It's not like the good old days!
You're here for fun but... Charity!
Thirsty...
That makes two of us!
Here!
- Help yourself.
- Don't be mean!
That's like closing the oasis
to a man in the desert!
Three turns of the timer
and you're done!
Here, water in easy reach.
Shame your hands are tied!
He's a villain. He's a maggot.
Drink!
He's thirsty.
Why not give him water?
Beautiful... Beautiful!
Beautiful!
Thank you, good people.
In a moment, Esmeralda will stun you
with Djali, the magic goat!
What are you doing?
Words cannot feed me.
By the way, I got married.
Married?
In a rather strange way.
But to a beautiful woman.
You abandoned God
to have this Egyptian girl?
I've not touched her,
if that's what interests you!
But you say man and wife?
She's a simple, charming girl.
Fond of dancing and the outdoors.
Swear you did nothing!
I tried to.
On the wedding night.
- Through the door, I saw...
- Stop!
the most beautiful...
- Gringoire!
- Excuse me, Master.
Work!
Here is Djali, who not only reads
but can also write.
This goat's knowledge has no bounds.
It's a miracle.
Letters hold no secrets from her.
Today, she has only one name
on her mind.
She read it shining in the stars.
It's a beautiful name meaning,
"the Sun".
Witchcraft!
Phoebus!
How incredibly modest you are!
To slay a dragon
and not tell your betrothed!
The dragon was more of a gargoyle!
Whatever!
The girls have been excited for days.
Neptune has suffered.
And the monks expect him
at the abbey.
Lucky Neptune!
Am I jealous?
I am loved by a mermaid
and have the right to love her back.
- What words!
- What feelings! From the heart.
Let your heart speak.
Had I a sister,
I would prefer you to her.
Had I gold,
I would lay it at your feet.
Had I a harem,
you would be my favourite.
- Look, your Egyptian!
- My Egyptian?!
The one you saved.
I heard she had a white goat.
Possibly. It was dark,
I didn't get a good look.
Her dancing draws crowds.
May I be jealous before our wedding?
Chase her away to make me happy.
Easy! I'll give the orders.
Prove your love to me...
Chase her off yourself!
You left me all alone
in the middle of the night.
Didn't expect to see me?
I did.
- Didn't forget me?
- Didn't try.
You are deep in my memory.
Here... How could I forget?
- What are you doing here?
- Following orders.
Be off with you!
The Place de Grève
is good enough for you lot!
Goodbye! If my friends go, I go.
Can we meet again?
Why not?
- Tonight?
- Where?
The same place.
Where you left me.
The little house.
Will you come?
Perhaps.
Until tonight, Sun!
Mother, he loves me so!
Like your father loved me!
Where to now? "The Golden Cat"?
- I have a date.
- But I'll fall down without you!
Anyway, Esmeralda can wait,
as she's so in love with you!
Maybe she's too impatient.
You can't abandon a friend
for a woman!
This is a farewell party!
- Farewell? Why?
- Because...
I'm turning to crime.
Thanks to my brother!
You won't see me again.
Unless it's to arrest me
or put a noose round my neck.
That's your job, after all.
My head's spinning.
Goodnight, villain!
In a poor man's bed
you have rich dreams.
You were helping me to walk, too!
Stop!
Listen!
The statue's speaking.
I thought you were two statues,
mind you.
- You have an appointment?
- With love.
And may I inform you...
it's with the Queen of Egypt
and her pyramids!
You speak both lies and the truth.
- You must be from Heaven!
- You are pitiful!
Pitiful? Me?!
He has a way with words!
Walk with me, statue.
Tell me some miserable things.
There's nothing like misery
to cheer me up.
Help me cross the Red Sea.
I'm stuck between two types of wine!
Don't go to your appointment.
The woman is married.
So what's new?
I'll be married soon, too.
Why should love
only sleep with marriage?
See that light?
It's time to say goodnight!
She's married and pure!
You can't!
Not even her husband has touched her.
Attacked by a hunchback,
left by her man,
protected by a shadow!
She must be a real queen.
- A queen waiting for her king!
- Have pity!
- Pity on whom?
- On her!
On her husband and his jealousy!
Goodnight, shadow... and thanks.
She's been waiting upstairs.
- For long?
- Love knows no time!
No, don't kiss me yet.
I'd like...
all women to be in love with you.
Especially the most beautiful.
And I'd like...
...you to pass them by.
- Jealous already?
A little.
What is beauty compared to me?
Ugliness!
What if I were jealous?
- Of all men?
- Of your husband.
Gringoire? If you saw him,
your jealousy would fade.
So you did marry?
Yes, but only to save his life.
I didn't give him mine.
That's for me alone.
I'm keeping it for the man I love!
Have you yearned for love?
Yes, but I have been happy.
Happiness is a gypsy's trade.
- But I was waiting for love.
- Have you found it?
Does he love me?
Don't doubt it.
If he loves me, as I do him...
- If he truly loves me...
- Child...
I have spoken
meaningless words of love
just to make someone happy.
My love for you is so true,
I've no reason to speak falsely.
Had I a sister, I'd love you more.
Had I gold, I'd give you all.
- Had I a harem...
- You'd be my favourite!
Liar!
I know the song.
- But what did I say to hurt you?
- Nothing. The same as all the others.
The same song.
I'm not sad because you lied...
but because I still love you.
I have no use for it now.
Help! Help!
A witch has stabbed the Captain!
I can no longer write.
Maybe you can eat!
She often left
without saying anything.
But never with no sign of life
or fidelity.
Flowers in a vase...
Wine in a jug...
- Some money in your pocket!
- True.
Now, here I am,
either a widower or a cuckold.
No, I trust her.
If she left me for another,
she wouldn't hide it.
I'm worried.
She's so beautiful.
Beauty and happiness
are like game that is tracked,
watched and hunted.
- Just tell me if he's alive.
- Silence, woman!
You are a gypsy witch,
in contact with the Devil,
who is in the form of the goat
that is your accomplice!
What are you saying?
The Devil? You hear, Djali?
Guards, stop them talking!
If this goat resists exorcism,
it will be sent either to the stake
or the gallows!
A name-writing goat!
A man killed by a witch!
A coin turned into a leaf!
It's obvious.
Bring the witnesses!
- Do you recognise the accused?
- It's her!
And is that her evil-smelling goat?
My poor room was covered in blood.
The loveliest, cleanest one,
covered in blood!
And the poor Captain
lying in it!
The girl dancing, her goat laughing!
- I swear it was!
- Madame Falourdel...
tell us of the dark man
who came and went like magic!
With the smell of sulphur and blood!
It was surely he
who changed the coin into a leaf.
Here it is!
Pass it round!
A chestnut leaf
that sheds no light on an affair
that is straightforward.
The witch stabbed the Captain!
It was her knife!
True, the weapon is against her,
but...
Continue, Master Frollo.
As an expert in witchcraft,
we'll hear you.
I want to say...
There was this strange apparition.
A demon, Master Frollo?
Who knows?
Woman!
- Did you see the dark man?
- No, but he was there.
- You saw him?
- As I see you!
So it was human. What did he do?
As you well know...
He turned a coin into the leaf
and disappeared.
Escort the witnesses!
He's clearly a dimwit!
But he was witness
to some disturbing events.
It is often the simpletons
that see hidden demons.
It's written in demonology texts.
Could it be the demon...
...and not the Egyptian
that stabbed the Captain?
So you think she is innocent?
- Maybe.
- But you're not certain?
Girl, you should confess.
It will save you pain.
Kill me if that's what you want.
But just tell me if he's alive.
Yes, thanks to God. Happy?
Happy?
He's alive and you ask if I'm happy?
So why am I here?
He must have told you I'm innocent.
His statement says he recalls nothing.
He didn't defend me?!
Although he knows it wasn't me.
Or, if he does know...
it's even more horrible,
more sad.
It's of no matter.
I'm happy nonetheless.
I did him no harm.
- Love saved his life.
- Love...
Life...
Those are the words of a witch!
Of a most dangerous witch!
And the demonic dark man...
even if he did the stabbing,
it was while he was under the spell
of this witch.
Woman, do you still deny it?
Given the obstinacy of the accused,
I demand an inquisition.
Agreed.
Do you still deny the facts?
There is nothing to deny.
None of what you say is true.
None of it!
Then I am forced
to carry out my duty.
Where shall we start?
The foot clamp.
Take that away!
Proceed.
Stop!
Do you admit your contract with evil?
Evil? Yes, I know evil.
I'll confess what you want.
We only want the truth.
- Speak.
- I'm in pain. Give me a moment.
Speak!
I know the forces of evil.
I killed a bird for singing too well.
I pushed a child in the Seine
for laughing gaily.
Don't bother us with that!
Did you stab Captain Phoebus?
Yes, I stabbed him
while he was kissing me.
And I danced with the dark man.
Djali is the devil and my husband.
His real name is Gringoire,
King of Rats.
The truth is out. Take it off.
That wasn't too bad.
You'll still be able to dance.
Please witness that we proceeded
as gently as possible.
- But it hurt.
- Humanity obliges me to say
your confession condemns you to hang.
On a day that pleases the King,
you'll be taken to confess
at Notre Dame,
and from there
to the Place de Grève,
where you will be hanged
on the city gallows.
At the Court of Miracles,
I was afraid of the rope and gallows.
But now it seems so simple.
So simple!
At Notre Dame, come and see
The woman hang from the gallows tree
It's a terrible thing
To see a young girl swing
Is there no more pity
In this God-forsaken city?
Alive today
Tomorrow the rope
Sweet Lord Jesus, is there hope?
We burn or hang so many witches
we don't their names.
This gypsy girl
So I sing
Killed a captain
In the service of the King...
What's so good
What's so cruel
Do you hear me?
How do we understand
A soul so dark
And a face so soft?
I always like to see
a pretty girl in a gown!
Are they hanging the goat?
Last year, they hanged a pig!
At Notre Dame, come and see
The woman swing from the gallows tree
Alive today, tomorrow the rope
Sweet Jesus...
Master Judge!
Sanctuary!
Man's justice ends
at the Cathedral door.
Sanctuary!
Don't be afraid.
The rope... has gone.
I'm even uglier when I laugh. But...
I smile when I'm happy.
This is where I live.
Make yourself at home.
That's my bed.
Away!
- I was stupid when I fetched you...
- Keep away!
I'm going.
If you need me... blow on this.
I can hear it.
Please...
Don't be afraid.
You brought me water.
I'll bring you food.
I'll put it there.
Stay inside or they'll kill you.
If they kill you...
I'll die.
What's he been up to all this time?
He's all alone. Maybe he's asleep.
Nobody comes here to sleep.
Maybe he's dead.
Creatures from Hell!
What do you want?
She's guilty, you hear?!
Guilty of living! Guilty of being!
Guilty like you! Like this dimwit!
Guilty like me!
Now it's over...
May her soul rest in peace.
And my soul! Mine!
God! What about mine?!
Go away!
Alive! You're alive!
Who brought you here?
God or the Devil only know...
I know you!
You're the liar from my trial.
You were the worst one of all.
- Listen...
- You accused me
and then they tortured me.
- You're the dark man.
- Quiet!
The dark man who stabbed Phoebus
was you.
- Forgive me.
- Why did you want him dead?
Why did you want me dead?
What do you want of me?
You ask what I want with you?!
Sanctuary!
He was the one who told me
to go and fetch you.
I know. I realise now.
I fear you less than him.
Don't go. Don't leave me alone.
- Can't hear...
- You... sleep... there.
Why are you hiding?
You don't want me to look?
In a land where they looked like you
they'd throw stones at me.
I've always been ugly.
Always scared people.
I didn't care.
But to scare you...
brings me pain.
For me?
With this,
my hanging gown is almost pretty.
My foot doesn't hurt.
The judge was right.
I can still dance.
Look!
That's Big Marie.
She made me deaf.
But we're still friends.
The music is for you!
Only for you!
- The bells have gone mad!
- It's the gypsy!
Fine music for a fine queen.
Charity!
- Do you like them?
- Yes.
Thank you, Quasimodo.
See? You'll be fine here with me.
And the birds.
But they fly away.
Poor Quasimodo...
Do you really think
we'll stay here together all my life?
They are bad down there.
Phoebus!
He didn't even look.
And yet he knows I'm here.
Do you want him to come?
I saw it in your eyes when you called.
It was just a memory.
Yes, go and fetch him!
I want to see him
to tell him I no longer love him.
And that I also was only pretending.
Go!
Sanctuary...
To think that a pagan creature
of the Devil
can be safe in the House of God!
Sit down, Phoebus, you're wounded.
By her!
Fleur de Lys is more wounded than I.
I wish to apologise to her.
How long will she stay up there
mocking our laws?
- Years, perhaps.
- She's wild.
She'll try to escape.
We'll see her
...and we'll have her.
- Hang her, you mean?
Hang her!
Won't that be just?
I am a soldier.
Even if my heart can forgive,
I will always obey
the laws of the King.
Well said!
Phoebus, I have nothing to hide.
To forget her sorrow,
Fleur de Lys has also found sanctuary.
In the Abbey, on our land,
which may become yours.
- You allow me to...
- She doesn't want to see you.
That means she's waiting for you.
- He looks happy.
- He's married.
To a witch!
Wait! Don't go.
She's up there.
Good for her. That way she'll live.
Take her flowers.
She likes flowers. Make her happy.
I told her I'd fetch you.
- Let me by.
- No.
She wants you to come.
She loves you!
If she didn't, I'd kill you!
Don't worry, Djali.
I won't be too naughty.
At first,
I won't say I don't love him.
And then,
I'll show how happy I am to see him.
He wouldn't come.
I brought you some flowers.
I got them down there.
You're crying.
I was lying.
He's coming. He told me himself.
He bought the flowers for you.
You're a bad liar.
You're too honest.
Are you happy?
Poor Quasimodo!
If Phoebus had your heart,
the world would be beautiful.
You were right to consult
your friend from Touraine.
In God's name,
the sanctuary law is sacred.
The people would be up in arms.
And if that happens,
we'll end up killing them,
which will cost us a great deal.
At least the Bishop we've come to see
is an erudite man.
He will give excellent advice,
Master Frollo.
- Mercy!
- Sire, Mercy!
What good is the King's mercy
without the foresight of judges?
A weakness!
- I'm innocent!
- I wish it were true.
I'm not here to cause you grief
but to seek your advice.
- From me?
- Yes. I have a problem...
I'm sure you can shed some light.
Light?!
I haven't seen the sun in 14 years!
I was talking about your knowledge.
And they say solitude
helps the memory!
Sanctuary law! That's my problem.
- Sanctuary is...
- A wonderful thing! We know.
But we want to know
if there have been times
when the law was not broken, but...
- You know what I mean.
- Yes, Sire.
Sanctuary has been overruled
in the name of God and the State.
The Bishop of England, allowed
a magician to be arrested in church.
St. Louis, King of France,
did a similar thing at St. Paul's.
Enough! We won't forget this.
Mercy, Sire! Take pity!
Our Lady of Paris, forgive me.
I must punish the gypsy.
She is a witch
who is unworthy of your protection.
It will be this once,
and I'll donate a silver statue.
Lovelier than the one
I gave to Notre Dame of Ecouys.
Amen!
Poet, she's your wife!
- Not really.
- I know. Charity!
You will go to her for us.
Tell her we won't forget her.
- They won't let me up.
- Afraid of her guardian?
- Not exactly, but...
- Whatever! Just do it!
- Master, I wanted to ask...
- Not now.
About my wife...
If she were your wife before God,
I would pity you.
Why have they taken down
the Good Lord?
- He'll be back tomorrow.
- Once justice is done.
Thus, he won't see his House profaned.
Get it? The sanctuary law...
If we do nothing, you'll be a widower.
Go away, there's nothing to see.
Until tomorrow,
Notre Dame is not a place of worship.
Come with me, Quasimodo.
You can be saved.
No, I know...
You want to hurt her.
Sanctuary!
The gallows is waiting
Try to escape
Hang the executioner
Who's whistling in the yard
The gallows is waiting
The hangman's noose
Runs from Issy to Vanvre
Is made with sisal not with wheat
No one steals the hangman's noose.
- Whose is the horse?
- I'd let down my brother,
if I went into battle on foot.
I want to please him.
If I ever come across the cursed sowl,
he'll be blind, not one-eyed!
It's you. You scared me.
You look wonderful in that!
Old armour makes the best soup.
Blood soup!
Don't move!
Poets need models, like painters.
Thank you. You are stored in my mind.
There's a place for you in my epic.
Many shall die!
Alas!
Many shall die, alas.
If I were one of them,
this song for her,
by me, eaten by rats,
would later be sung by Esmeralda.
You don't risk dying, here.
If I were there I'd die of fright.
Then who would write my epic?
Who could describe fear like I?
This fear of fear...
In line, Egypt!
In line, Argot!
In line, Galilee!
Louis, Bishop of Paris!
I, Clopin, King of Coins,
Prince of Argot, Bishop of Fools,
declare...
If your church is sacred,
so is our sister!
If she is not, neither is your church!
Our sister, wrongly condemned,
has taken refuge inside!
You must give her sanctuary!
To save the church,
hand over the girl!
Or we'll take the girl
and pillage the church!
In the name of whatever,
I plant my banner.
May God protect you, Bishop of Paris!
Don't forget,
there are 40 chests of gold inside!
Forward! To work!
To work, locksmiths!
The sky is falling on us!
These men are afraid of anything!
These doors won't budge an inch!
Here's the ram to enter Notre Dame!
Charge!
Courage, gypsies!
Tear it down!
Don't be afraid. Go back to sleep.
They want to hurt you.
But I'll kill them first.
Stop!
They are my friends, my brothers!
Don't be afraid.
They are trying to rescue me!
There're many of them...
But you'll see!
It's alright. Go back to sleep.
To victory!
We have the ladder from the bridge!
To the battering ram!
To the gold!
Long live crime!
Sanctuary!
You want to hurt her, too.
By God, I have no faith, no law,
No fire, no place
No god, no king
My brother's soul
We condemn to Hell!
I have no soul
So I won't go!
Come on, the lock is giving!
They're coming in.
Come, I'll hide you.
One more charge
from the battering ram!
We'll have our hands on the gold!
Look, Mathias, it was worth it!
Cut them down!
Life is wonderful!
Charity for her, please.
My job is done!
Though she be dead, hang her!
She was judged and condemned.
They've gone.
It's over.
It's all your fault!
During the night of Esmeralda's death,
the grave diggers
took down her body from the gallows
and took it to the catacombs
at Montfaucon.
Two years after these incidents,
they found two skeletons,
one mysteriously holding the other
in a fond embrace.
When they tried to move them,
they turned to dust.